IN THE YEAR OF THE LORD 1247
Do you have any food?
I am very hungry.
Blow your hair out.
No one believes you're a boy.
I'm not afraid.
Wandering journeymen in the mountains
have told of the hero Robin Hood.
He protects the meek.
No one protects the meek.
And he was no hero.
He prays three times
a day and gives to the poor.
And he has won
the heart of Lady Marian. Isn't he a hero?
Lady Marian comes from
a robbery story told by a –
– who was unfortunately even more drunk than me.
She was Robin Hood's great love.
There is no greater
love for someone like him.
I know some people who have met
him. Do you want to hear a secret?
Me too.
He has never prayed so much as once.
These rumors that
have spread are nothing but lies.
He was a murderous robber –
– who possibly slit the throat
of a sheriff among many others.
People saw an opinion that didn't exist.
He was no hero.
He plundered and killed
only for pleasure.
Those you met...
Did they say he
regretted his misdeeds?
He was probably tired.
If you met the bandit Robin Hood –
– you should hurry away and
save the life you now have left.
and forgive us our sins.
Through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.
Who is your relative?
William Wainwright of Pickering.
Pickering...
Far?
Grandfather?
You should have washed yourself
or waited for the wind to change.
Or put your weight on the back leg.
That's all. You did well.
They sing lies –
– these cheap fools.
Lies about his heroism and goodness.
But the bloodguilt is old...
and generations of
his victims hunt him...
because in reality –
– was no one more evil and ruthless –
– than the murderous bandit Robin Hood –
– and his Little John.
Talk to Thomas.
– He was hanged down south. – Will?
They ripped him open.
I have no one else to ask.
What happened?
My name is Edward.
Who was Edward?
I met him on the road ten summers ago.
His brother had died, and he wanted
to grow rye and peas on his land.
No one knew what Edward looked like...
So I killed him. Now I'm Edward.
And Margaret is a good wife to me.
– It's a good farm. – What happened?
A family exposed me. They took my farm.
Took my Margaret. Tried to take my life.
– We must fight for what
is mine. – It is not yours.
It's my family.
I'm tired, John.
Edward.
I'm tired, Edward.
It will be a magnificent
battle. One for the adventures.
– Are they strong? – Yes.
They are from an old lineage.
Reportedly Viking blood.
It is said that their great-grandfather once fought a bear.
It's going to be a mighty blow, Robin.
How many are they?
Four, five...
Together we can overcome them.
We're probably going to die.
Robin.
Robin!
Bread?
This is a good adventure.
A good adventure.
Do you remember when we met the potter?
Did we leave him naked, or did we kill him?
I tried to tell the story, and
someone said we left him naked.
But I couldn't remember.
You always told it well, Robin.
Why would we leave him naked?
I don't know.
Just kidding.
– We have never met a
potter. – What do you mean?
It never happened. It's just
a story you heard somewhere.
But if we had met a
potter, we would have killed him.
I would remember if it was a story.
Her.
Tell me about your wife.
Margaret.
She is a good woman.
A very good woman. She is God-fearing.
– She teaches me piety. – Describe her.
Should I describe her?
Describe...
Her hair is...
red.
– Red like? – Red like fresh blood.
No, not blood.
Something red that's good, just like her.
Red as...
the evening red.
Like the red of summer evening.
Margaret is a good wife...
with hair like the red of summer evening.
She cares about me –
– and I from her.
Robin, the land lies
open beyond the mountains.
There are many places to start over.
I don't intend to start over.
I intend to die a proper death.
Run, Hendrie!
– Run, Hendrie! – Edward!
Go away! Hendrie!
– Get the others! – Edward.
My beloved.
Take good care of little Margaret.
Don't worry.
You are safe. You
are safe, my daughter.
Let us pray.
Lord God –
– grant us the grace to
love you with all our hearts.
Pray with me.
And when we find you, we will love you –
– and hate the sins from which you have freed us.
For Jesus Christ. Amen.
Yes. Good.
Sorry.
That's how it was when I woke up.
– Cousin. – That's how it was when I woke up.
Sorry.
We call upon you, O Lord.
Show us mercy.
And grant us forgiveness.
O King of heaven and Lord of eternity.
Hear our prayers as we offer them.
And grant us forgiveness.
Look to the sick, bring
the captive here –
– help the widow and the orphan.
And grant us forgiveness.
We have sinned and gone astray.
Will you, the savior of all –
– save us?
And grant us forgiveness.
Show the penitent grace –
– and wash away the shame of sin.
And grant us forgiveness.
Amen.
Kill him!
Be careful!
Spare me!
– Margaret! – No!
John, no!
Little John!
Twenty winters ago
you murdered my cousin –
– Walter of Hathersage.
You have murdered my sons and my grandson.
As a family settlement,
I accept your life.
And your daughter's life!
–... murderous acts...
–... cruel crimes...
murderer of mother,
woman and child, for all eternity.
No...!
Your punishment awaits, Robin Hood.
You killed my sisters and brothers.
– Robin. – Punishment awaits, Robin Hood.
Robin.
I've heard stories about
a monastery far off the beaten track.
The prioress is older than anyone can remember.
She possesses healing power.
I'll take you out to her.
She'll make you well again.
I've heard incredible stories.
Robin, we have to leave you.
They're coming after us.
That's right.
Unusually so late.
But it won't stay put.
The long day is not that cold.
A man came with you.
He closed your wounds
with fire, and not unevenly.
You've been here for six days.
You have a stomach ulcer.
Severe fractures of the ribs and one leg.
Can you understand my words?
Where are we?
In the monastery of Saint Clement –
– where you can recover.
Which city?
There is no city.
Do you know the story of Saul?
What?
They say that there
was once a man named Saul –
– who threatened the Lord's disciples with murder.
He asked the high priest for
letters to Damascus, to the synagogues –
– to imprison both men
and women who belonged to the Way.
That's enough. Just a few drops.
It wasn't too painful, was it?
It wasn't.
My name is Sister Bridget.
What is your name?
Randolph.
I owe you an apology.
What is that supposed to say?
You begged me to let you die.
And I didn't.
– You said it was the
right thing. – I had a fever.
You don't have that anymore.
Rest now, Randolph.
Your body is covered with scars.
Do you wish to harm anyone in the monastery?
I don't.
Does evil follow you out here?
It doesn't.
You're not hurting them.
And then back to bed.
And then back to the door.
Then open the door.
Go as far as you want.
Can you row?
There is a boat on the shore to the west.
But you're welcome to stay
if you help in the orchard.
I am not a farmer.
Then you don't know how to hunt.
Yes, I do.
There is wildlife here on the island.
But you can't go hunting. You
can't even string a bow.
– I can do that. – It's mostly rabbits.
– Can you set traps? – Yes, I can.
Good. But no more than six traps.
Otherwise the population will perish.
Can you handle six traps?
I can handle six traps.
Well.
Then you can help in
the orchard the rest of the time.
Are you trying to escape?
You are quiet.
I am quiet and slow.
You were quiet –
– but you also have to be
slow. You are a cripple.
And you are a leper.
You can go
slow. We're safe here.
– That's a bit of a statement. You know
? – Yes, because she has given us security.
Priorind?
She was like us.
She experienced great sorrow, great pain.
Became a widow at a very young age.
But in her grief
she found the strength to heal us.
You don't look healed.
The prioress once told me
a story about a great philosopher.
The greatest philosopher of his time.
But one day his king turned against him –
– and threw him into a dungeon where
he was to be tortured and executed.
But in the philosopher's misery,
when he had nothing –
– an angel came to him and spoke to him.
And from her he learned that
it didn't matter –
– if the whole world were pure misery...
and only death awaited.
Because he had one thing no one
could touch or take away from him.
He had his mind.
And in his mind...
He had God.
It's never too late to find peace.
– What do you do? – I row every day.
Not everyone can transport people like
your friend, so I sail them.
– Will you sail me over? – No.
You can row yourself when you
have regained your strength.
Now watch your traps.
– I'm going hunting. – You can't.
Tell me, leper friend, what
happened to the great philosopher?
He was then, of course,
tortured and executed.
Of course.
The leper has come
with someone from the distant shore.
Father is dead.
How is the girl doing?
Now you should see my trees.
It's elderberry.
The berries should be picked late in the summer.
Do they know what you used to be?
Speak to me on this side
for the sake of my hearing.
The pears will ripen immediately afterwards.
– And what was I before?
– You were probably a mercenary.
Yes, it's safe to say.
We have a special appearance.
– Do you remember the trees? – Pears and elder.
Wonderful.
Some of them know.
But the prioress doesn't care
who we've been.
The apples should be picked in the fall.
Has she told you about what
happened to her?
The prioress is taking care of the girl. Talk
to her if you are worried.
What kind of trees were those?
Pears, apples and elderberries.
Wonderful.
This is the last bloodletting.
But your body is still far from healed.
You are tired.
Yes, that's me.
But I've been tired before.
The child is not sleeping.
What has she been exposed to?
Horrible things.
– Has she told her
story? – She doesn't speak.
She neither eats nor sleeps.
What is her name?
Margaret.
Who is she?
I met her father.
A farmer.
– He's dead. – Obviously.
– And her mother? – She's probably dead too.
– How? –
I don't know. She walked away.
Was she killed?
Perhaps.
You are good at lying.
Did the child see that?
It is possible.
It's devastating for a child to see.
I feel bad for your friend.
Not.
Should I pray for him?
If you want.
What was his name?
Edward.
Edward...
Let not your heart be troubled:
believe in God, believe also in me.
In my Father's house there are many mansions.
And when I have prepared
a place for you –
– I will come again and take you to me –
– so that you also may be where I am.
And where I go, you know the way.
– She has a knife. – She cut me!
Margaret.
Don't worry.
Margaret, just relax.
She doesn't know the island.
There are tidal waves.
Margaret!
Aflever.
The men who hurt you...
Do they know you're here?
What is my name?
Say my name.
Randolph.
Just exactly.
Who is Little John?
That name is nonsense
and should never be mentioned.
If you mention it, the cat will come
at night and bite your tongue off.
Don't worry.
Go to sleep.
I'm keeping an eye on the storm.
Lie down.
Close your eyes.
Sleep safe.
Sleep.
Thank you for bringing her back.
It was so little.
Do you know the history of the monastery?
The best.
In prehistoric times
it was the sanctuary of the Druids.
They worshipped unknown gods.
Worship them out here.
But then the Romans came and
sensed the magic here –
– so they built their temples.
But people after people have sensed
it and have come to worship...
Countless gods and tribes who
wouldn't even be able to talk to each other.
And yet we are all
drawn towards this place.
Do you believe there is magic on the island?
I believe it possesses a power.
And I have seen the power of stories.
They can be used to make
people commit atrocities.
And then those
atrocities become stories...
and stories.
No. You shouldn't believe any of them.
We can't take care of them.
Knives can cut bread as well as meat.
It's about balance.
Does balance matter?
If balance meant nothing –
– we wouldn't be here.
This world wouldn't...
be here, and...
we wouldn't exchange those words.
Have you ever considered that?
The astonishing
precision of the balance over such an immense period of time.
The balance it takes to
create any word –
– which can come out between two lips and...
understood by two minds.
Randolph.
Not.
Aren't you hungry?
Aren't you?
I'm going to die soon.
How do you know that?
I can feel it inside.
How does it feel?
It feels right.
There is someone.
It has been busy on the lake.
First around the feet. Small cuts.
Good. And the other one.
Well.
And now in front, down through the stomach.
Good. No.
Look here.
Such.
Take the second one. Like this.
You are a brave young man.
Thank you, sister.
Are you hungry, Arthur?
Yes, sister.
Sarah is making
you a hearty meal tonight. Stewed herring.
– Do you like it? – Yes.
Where are you from, Arthur?
– My family farm in
the Keswick area. – Keswick?
– Ja, hr. – Randolph.
Randolph... In the Keswick area.
The leper says
you're looking for your niece.
– Yes, I do. – Were you assaulted?
– Yes. – On the road?
– Yes. – You're safe here.
Which way?
The road to Keswick, Mr.
– Praise the Lord that you
survived. – I do.
How about pears in honey
for dessert for your courage?
Thank you, sister.
Little Margaret...
That Arthur... did you see
him before you came out to the monastery?
Margaret.
Those men...
The men who hurt your father...
Did you see their faces?
Dad said I should run.
Dad stopped praying.
He was angry.
He prayed in his mind.
What is dad's name?
Your father is your father.
Come here with it.
Beautiful craftsmanship.
Can you see it bends more here?
It must be smoothed out so that it bends evenly.
This piece needs to be sliced ​​thinner.
Can you make one for me?
Should I make you a bow?
Excellent.
Today I was reminded of a
story by the poet Lucretius.
He wrote about something called atoms.
If you separate trees, people and stones –
– it is the smallest,
invisible parts that make up...
everything in creation.
And these atoms float
through the void and...
sometimes changes course for no reason.
The tiniest little bit.
And if not that...
small unpredictable change –
– forced the atoms to –
– to intertwine with each other...
nothing under heaven would exist.
Good. Harder.
Like this. Good.
Harder. Now I'm going to help you.
Day the day of the.
Good. That's how it should be. Good.
Which one is best for your bow?
Let's take a look.
They are both nice.
– Margaret! – Come and play!
Let's play tag. You count.
– You can do that. – No, it's your turn.
Arthur...
– Can you set traps? – Yes.
Good. I need
someone to take over. Come on.
Does your family have land?
Yes.
How many are you?
I don't know.
Is everything okay?
Yes, yes.
I'm not as young as I once was.
I could use a hand.
Not.
It was a bit of a blow otherwise.
– Yes. – Who was it?
A man.
Some men.
– Bandits. – A man? Bandits?
– Yes. – Can I see?
That's a real blow.
– You're lucky to have
survived, kid. – Yes.
– Be grateful
to be alive. – Yes.
He used a staff.
You're lucky he didn't
cut your head off.
Randolph!
Moshe!
The prioress says you must come!
Are you in severe pain?
Do you remember the trees?
Pears, apples and elderberries.
Wonderful.
You are the most important person –
– in little Margaret's life.
I'm not important.
Think of all those whose lives you have crossed.
We matter to all of them.
Do you know the story of Guy of Gisborne...
and Robin Hood?
Yes.
They say you killed him.
– Did you really behead him? –
You speak in delusion, leper friend.
I don't say a word to anyone.
But you shouldn't lie to
a man on his deathbed.
So...
Did you really behead him?
There was no Guy of Gisborne.
It was just one of many stories.
But I have beheaded others.
You really don't remember?
The best.
Think about the name.
The gentleman Guy of Gisborne.
But you didn't behead him.
You cut off his ear.
You said –
– that in another life
you would have toasted him.
Do you remember that?
We have apparently found another life.
There is one atrocity I
would ask you not to commit.
You must tend the orchard
until you too die.
Serving the Prioress...
and people who come and go to the monastery.
But at no time...
in these...
good and peaceful years...
You must tell the prioress
who you really are.
Why?
Because...
one of the nameless and faceless
dead in the dark recesses of your mind...
was in another life...
her fiancé.
Promise me...
Robin.
Promise me.
Goodbye, Bridget.
Arthur.
Come on.
There is a child on the distant shore.
Maybe it's your niece.
The leper said you
're looking for your missing niece.
Yes.
– Could it be
her? – We'll see.
I can't see anyone.
We are waiting.
Maybe they'll return.
What is your name?
Arthur.
Don't waste your time lying
to me. What's your real name?
Godwyn
You are deciding, Godwyn,
whether to do the deed yourself –
– or pick up your family.
– What deed? – How many
have you killed, Godwyn?
How many children have you killed?
I've killed so many
that I can't count them.
Longer than you have lived,
I have killed their relatives –
– I killed an eternity
ago. I don't remember them.
And they meant nothing to me, but...
their brothers, children and
grandchildren remember me.
So now I have to kill them.
Time after time.
In various shapes that shadow the path...
ongoing, and it never stops.
It's a curse, Godwyn.
And you call it down upon
yourself, even if you do it out of duty.
It doesn't take care of your duty.
This world only cares about blood.
And blood is the only thing it gives back.
But do you want to kill a child, Godwyn?
Do you want to take the blame for
the murder of a little girl?
The best.
Is your father dead?
And your uncles?
I am the oldest one left.
Who else is alive?
My mother.
My aunts.
– My sisters. – You have a home, Godwyn.
– Yes. – Go home.
Tell the family that the blood debt has been paid.
They will all be paid one day.
Sleep in your own bed.
Cherish the life you
can still share with your loved ones.
And if you return –
– have you wasted this chance
to have a life that I am giving you now.
And then I'll cut your throat
and never give you another thought.
Go then.
And don't look back.
I thought you had left.
I am Robin the Outlaw.
You should know that. I am a monster.
I am not someone named Randolph.
I am the Outlaw, Robin Hood.
Avoid...
Tell me I have to travel...
So I'm leaving now.
Go to bed.
– Bridget... – Lie down.
You burned my husband alive.
I dream that he was already dead,
but why else did you close the door?
For what seemed like an eternity,
I searched the ashes of our home.
And he looked so small.
He was huddled in the corner,
and most of him was gone.
But despite my dreams
, I know he was alive.
Because to the very end,
he embraced our children.
Randolph?
It's me.
People talk about Robin Hood.
Tells his stories.
It's all lies.
Lies I told a long time ago...
so the fools...
followed me into the darkness.
Robin.
What have they done to you?
Don't be afraid.
We'll have to get you out of here.
I'm saving little Margaret.
And then we start over together.
Edward.
Tell me about your wife.
My wife?
Margaret.
My wife, Margaret.
Describe her.
Should I describe her?
Her hair is...
red like...
the evening red.
Like the red of summer evening.
Red as...
the evening red of summer.
Robin.
Have you found your hard death?
I'm ready to end it.
I owe you this life.
It's horrible.
But I owe you this life.
You don't owe me anything.
I have never taken a life.
It can be like pruning a flower.
– It shouldn't be.
– No, it shouldn't be.
But it could be.
I help those who come out here on the island.
I heal them.
I beg you.
Heal me.
Little Margaret.
Your father's name was John.
I knew him for many years –
– before he became your father.
I met him –
– on the way over a bridge the other day...
over a rushing river.
He was a stubborn rad.
He wouldn't bend.
Not for anyone.
Not even me.
So we fought –
– on that bridge.
Went on the attack. Back and forth.
I gave him one on the side of the head.
He hit me in the stomach.
And I was staggering on that bridge.
Splash!
I landed face down on the seagull.
When I managed to drag myself up –
– soaked...
we embraced each other.
We called your father –
– Little John.
And we lived for many years...
like outlaws in the green forest.
And we partied...
We...
We gave silver to the meek.
But we had stolen the silver.
We had stolen it...
from...
from evil people.
Can you understand that?
Evil people.
From the lighthouse...
didn't want
me to tell you...
because he loved you so much.
You must never tell anyone.
Not even the children you play with.
You must never mention your father's name.
There are evil people out there.
And they are angry with your father.
And that's why they're angry with you.
Can we keep that secret?
I can keep that
secret, little Margaret.
Can you?
Well.
Come to me.
Day here.
Why was he small?
What?
Why was my father called little?
Because he was little when I found him.
Like you.
Put it on.
Bend it with your leg like you saw me do.
Well.
Go to the window.
Put an arrow on the bow.
Find a point –
– where the water meets the sky.
Pull the arrow up to the mouth...
and hold it.
I say guy.
And when I do...
then you don't let go.
You just don't hold on anymore.
Well.
Keep your eye on the target.
Your body is moving all the time.
Feel –
– when the arrow takes flight.
You find a dance.
Hold on to it until I say, dude.
You are strong.
Note...
it swayed.
Den in.
Guy.
Translated by Lasse Schmidt Danish Video Text